so a distributed last level cache is
logically a single cache
in that a data block will not be
replicated
like it would be in private caches where
if two or three or four cores for
example read a block each of their
caches would have that block and thus
really the total capacity of the caches
is not how much memory we are covering
because some memory appears many times
possibly in these caches
a last level cache that is distributed
is logically still one cache
meaning if its capacity is let's say
four megabytes then we really cover four
megabytes of memory without any
replication
but this distributed cache is sliced up
so that each tile which contains a core
and possibly local caches now also
contains a part of this cache so now
what we have is
in our mesh
we have a tile
that contains a core a level one cache a
level two cache and a slice of the l3
cache
so if this slice here that we use per
core is let's say one megabyte
is really n times one megabytes where n
is the number of cores so now as you can
see
if we use four cores we get four
megabytes with 16 cores we have 16
megabytes so we get what we want
the big cache
that is there to prevent memory accesses
is growing with the number of cores but
it doesn't have a single entry point in
fact each slice has its own entry point
so if we want the data that is in this
slice we have to route our message to
that slice
if we want the data that resides in
another slice we send a message there
if the data is spread among the slices
so that
all of them get equal demands for the
data then the network traffic would be
nicely distributed across our chip so
that none of the links get over utilized
but if we have a level two miss
in a particular core how do we know
which slice of the level three cache
to ask for the data one simple solution
is to spread the cash round robin among
slices by cash index so if we have our
level 3 cash with let's say 1024 sets
slice 0 gets set 0 slice 1 gets set 1
etc and then let's say that we have 8
cores then slice 7 gets set 7. slice 0
gets set 8 set 9 is in slice 1 again and
so on so now we can relatively easily
after we break down the address to
access the cache we know the set number
and
the least significant
three bits in this case tell us which
slice to ask if we have
even more cores then the number of sets
in the cache will grow and as a result
the number of bits
that we need to tell us which slice we
have is growing and that means that the
number of bits in the index are growing
and we will need additional bits to tell
us in which set to look note that if we
sequentially access data then we will be
really looking at you know one set and
then the next set and then the next set
and this nicely spreads the load among
the slices of the level three cache
because sequential accesses are
basically going to be spread across the
entire chip however the spreading of
blocks round robin
across the entire chip may not be good
for locality
because a core is just as likely to
access something that is in the opposite
corner of the chip as it is to access
its own slice in which case there is no
on-chip network traffic whatsoever
so another way that can help with that
is that we spread the data around but
this time we spread it by page number so
all of the blocks that belong to the
same page would end up in the same slice
of the level three that helps because
now the operating system can map pages
so that it makes the accesses to l3 more
local for example here this score is
running a thread that has a stack
the pages that belong to that stack
should be those that end up in this
slice so that if we have a level two
miss we are very likely to access our
own local slice of the l3 cache of
course
some of the shared data will be us
elsewhere but this dramatically improves
the locality in terms of how far do we
need to go to get to the correct slice
of l3
any data that tends to be accessed by
one core can be now mapped by the
operating system so that it's usually
found in the local slice of the last
level cache